<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title>Functorium</title>
      <link>https://ananthakrishnagopal.github.io</link>
      <description>Explorations in Geometry, Scientific Computing, and Quantum Structures</description>
      <generator>Zola</generator>
      <language>en</language>
      <atom:link href="https://ananthakrishnagopal.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 17:42:00 +0800</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
          <title>About</title>
          <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 17:42:00 +0800</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://ananthakrishnagopal.github.io/about/</link>
          <guid>https://ananthakrishnagopal.github.io/about/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://ananthakrishnagopal.github.io/about/">&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m Ananthakrishna Gopal, and my work lives at the seam between abstract mathematics and practical computation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I began as a pure mathematician, fascinated by structures like differentiable stacks, cohomology, and higher categories. During my time at IISER Thiruvananthapuram, I immersed myself in the elegance of geometry and algebra—not just for their beauty, but for their surprising relevance to the world we live in.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That curiosity soon became a drive to apply theory in ways that matter, and over time I found myself moving fluently across disciplines. From Abstract Category Theory all the way to Scientific Computing and Machine Learning.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I’m a research engineer at Tata Consultancy Services, where I work on developing quantum algorithms, optimizing large-scale simulations, and bringing deep theoretical ideas into real-world software—spanning pharma, logistics, and materials science. I’ve co-authored publications, filed multiple patents, and led cross-disciplinary teams translating mathematical insight into enterprise-grade tools.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Functorium is my thinking space—a place to document, reflect, and share what I learn along the way. Whether I’m writing about geometric abstraction, numerical performance, or quantum models of computation, I return to the same question: how can structure become strategy?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If that’s a question that excites you too, welcome.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>Tensor-Factorized Hamiltonian Downfolding: A Geometric and Quantum Computing Perspective</title>
          <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 17:42:00 +0800</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://ananthakrishnagopal.github.io/drafts/02-07-2023-tfhd-geometric-perspective/</link>
          <guid>https://ananthakrishnagopal.github.io/drafts/02-07-2023-tfhd-geometric-perspective/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://ananthakrishnagopal.github.io/drafts/02-07-2023-tfhd-geometric-perspective/">&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High-dimensional Hermitian operators are central to many computational problems in quantum physics, numerical linear algebra, and signal processing. However, traditional methods for handling these operators suffer from exponential scaling in both memory and computation—often requiring \( O(N^4) \) storage and \( O(N^7) \) operations for systems of size \( N \). Enter &lt;strong&gt;Tensor-Factorized Hamiltonian Downfolding (TFHD)&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: a structured, exact operator compression framework that leverages algebraic geometry, tensor networks, and quantum computing principles to tame this complexity.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;geometric-foundations-algebraic-varieties-and-tensor-rank&quot;&gt;Geometric Foundations: Algebraic Varieties and Tensor Rank&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its core, TFHD operates within the algebraic variety \( V_{k,R} \) of Hermitian operators with CP-rank at most \( R \). Each step of the downfolding process defines a rational transformation&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$
\pi_k : V_{k,R} \rightarrow V_{k-1,R&#x27;},
$$&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;reducing dimensionality while preserving spectral properties. This geometric perspective connects TFHD to the theory of &lt;strong&gt;secant varieties&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;low-rank tensor models&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, offering a principled way to navigate the manifold of structured operators.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;Canonical Polyadic (CP) decomposition&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; plays a key role in this geometric formulation. By expressing quartic interaction tensors as low-rank outer products, TFHD compresses storage from \( O(k^4) \) to \( O(kR) \), enabling scalable contractions and efficient manipulation. Moreover, the framework preserves this low-rank structure across transformations, with controlled rank growth bounded by polynomial factors under mode elimination.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;quantum-computing-implications-block-encoding-for-quantum-tensor-contraction&quot;&gt;Quantum Computing Implications: Block-Encoding for Quantum Tensor Contraction&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From a quantum computing standpoint, TFHD provides a principled architecture for performing &lt;strong&gt;quantum tensor contractions&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; via &lt;strong&gt;block-encoded circuit primitives&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. While both TFHD and tensor hypercontraction (THC) reduce the dimensionality of high-order tensors using CP decompositions, TFHD uniquely emphasizes &lt;strong&gt;structured algebraic compression&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;quantum circuit synthesis&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; rooted in exact operator geometry.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each term in the CP decomposition of a downfolded operator corresponds to a product of low-rank factors, which can be &lt;strong&gt;individually block-encoded&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; into unitaries with logarithmic overhead in rank and system size. This enables a &lt;strong&gt;quantum-native tensor contraction model&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, where multilinear contractions—normally intractable classically due to tensor dimensionality—are implemented as &lt;strong&gt;compositions of shallow block-encoded circuits&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than treating the tensor decomposition as merely a pre-processing step for Hamiltonian simulation, TFHD &lt;strong&gt;uses the factorized structure as the basis of the quantum computation itself&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. This makes tensor contraction a &lt;strong&gt;direct target for quantum execution&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, with contractions compiled into controlled unitary blocks and ancilla-mediated arithmetic.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Crucially, TFHD’s emphasis on &lt;strong&gt;preserving the CP structure throughout mode elimination and renormalization&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; means that contraction complexity remains bounded across successive transformations. This allows for scalable &lt;strong&gt;quantum evaluation of expectation values, overlaps, and projected operator actions&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, without incurring exponential gate depth.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to THC, which often relies on orbital-localized truncations or fixed quadrature approximations, TFHD provides &lt;strong&gt;a systematic pathway from algebraic compression to hardware-efficient quantum circuits&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. The result is a tensor contraction framework in which &lt;strong&gt;quantum and classical resources are tightly co-designed&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, allowing quantum processors to focus on the multilinear core of the computation while offloading structural optimization to classical preprocessing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TFHD thus opens the door to &lt;strong&gt;quantum-accelerated tensor contraction engines&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; for applications in electronic structure, quantum materials, and correlated dynamics—bridging structured linear algebra with block-encoded circuit design.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;operator-renormalization-without-approximation&quot;&gt;Operator Renormalization Without Approximation&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The iterative elimination of modes via nilpotent conjugation mirrors the spirit of &lt;strong&gt;renormalization group (RG) flow&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, but with a crucial difference: TFHD is exact. Rather than coarse-graining and truncating high-energy states, it performs an algebraically rigorous transformation that retains the full spectrum. This exactness is rooted in the &lt;strong&gt;nilpotency&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; of the generator \( \eta_k \), ensuring that all higher-order commutators vanish beyond degree 2.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, viewing TFHD through the lens of &lt;strong&gt;tensor networks&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, the procedure resembles a &lt;strong&gt;Matrix Product Operator (MPO)&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; construction with bounded bond dimension. Successive CP contractions correspond to &lt;strong&gt;low-rank tensor trains&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, supporting scalable classical and quantum simulations.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;challenges-and-open-directions&quot;&gt;Challenges and Open Directions&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite its power, several open questions remain:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can we derive tighter bounds on CP rank growth across arbitrary mode elimination sequences?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do low-rank approximations affect eigenvalue accuracy?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does the topology of \( V_{k,R} \) influence convergence or error propagation in practical implementations?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can TFHD be extended to non-Hermitian operators or continuous-index tensor fields?&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These questions invite further exploration at the intersection of &lt;strong&gt;differential geometry&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;representation theory&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;categorical algebra&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, where TFHD naturally extends to a functorial transformation between operator categories.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tensor-Factorized Hamiltonian Downfolding represents a paradigm shift in how we handle high-dimensional operators. By combining &lt;strong&gt;exact algebraic manipulation&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;low-rank tensor geometry&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;quantum-efficient encoding&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, TFHD enables the treatment of previously intractable problems in quantum simulation and beyond.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For technical professionals in quantum computing, applied mathematics, and theoretical physics, TFHD opens new pathways for scalable, structure-preserving computation—bridging abstract mathematical structures with real-world algorithmic impact.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the complete paper, refer to our paper: &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;arxiv.org&#x2F;abs&#x2F;2303.07051&quot;&gt;Tensor Factorized Hamiltonian Downfolding To Optimize The Scaling Complexity Of The Electronic Correlations Problem on Classical and Quantum Computers&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
</description>
      </item>
      <item>
          <title>TFHD: Compressing Quantum Reality Like a JPEG</title>
          <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>Unknown</author>
          <link>https://ananthakrishnagopal.github.io/posts/tfhd-compressing-quantum-reality-like-a-jpeg/</link>
          <guid>https://ananthakrishnagopal.github.io/posts/tfhd-compressing-quantum-reality-like-a-jpeg/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://ananthakrishnagopal.github.io/posts/tfhd-compressing-quantum-reality-like-a-jpeg/">&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simulating quantum systems—molecules, materials, or electronics at the atomic level—unlocks breakthroughs in science and industry, but it’s a computational beast. With 1000 orbitals (slots where electrons can sit), traditional methods need to store ~\( 10^{12} \) numbers and perform ~\( 10^{21} \) calculations, overwhelming even supercomputers. This slows progress in drug discovery, materials design, and quantum computing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tensor-Factorized Hamiltonian Downfolding (TFHD)&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; is a game-changer. Think of it as &lt;strong&gt;JPEG compression for quantum physics&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: it shrinks complex quantum data into a compact form, slashing computational costs while preserving critical physical properties, like energy levels. By compressing data once at the start into low-rank Canonical Polyadic (CP) tensors and working entirely in this format, TFHD makes impossible simulations possible.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-challenge-quantum-complexity-overload&quot;&gt;The Challenge: Quantum Complexity Overload&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In quantum mechanics, the &lt;strong&gt;Hamiltonian&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; describes a system’s energy and interactions, like how electrons move in a molecule. For \( N \) orbitals, it includes:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simple interactions&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (electrons hopping between orbitals), needing ~\( O(N^2) \) data points.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Complex interactions&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (electrons repelling each other), stored in a four-dimensional array \( h_{abcd}^2 \), needing ~\( O(N^4 )\) data points.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Hamiltonian acts in a \( 2^N \)-dimensional space, and computing properties like energy levels requires ~\( O(N^7) \) operations. For \( N = 1000 \), this means a trillion numbers and a sextillion calculations—far beyond current computing power, limiting applications like drug design or battery optimization.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-tfhd-works-compression-without-loss&quot;&gt;How TFHD Works: Compression Without Loss&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TFHD compresses the Hamiltonian into a &lt;strong&gt;CP tensor&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; format, representing complex data with fewer numbers, like a compressed image. This compression happens once at the start, and all calculations stay in CP format without further recompression. The process is exact, preserving all physical properties, and follows four steps:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-one-time-compression-to-cp-format&quot;&gt;1. One-Time Compression to CP Format&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The complex interaction data \( h_{abcd}^2 \) in the Hamiltonian \( H^{(k)} \) is simplified using &lt;strong&gt;Cholesky factorization&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, reshaping it into a manageable form. This is approximated once into a CP tensor:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[
h_{abcd}^2 \approx \sum_{r=1}^R B_{ar}^1 B_{br}^2 B_{cr}^3 B_{dr}^4,
\]&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where \( R \) (the CP rank) is small, and each \( B^m \) is a matrix of size \( N \times R \). This cuts storage from ~\( O(N^4 )\) to ~\( O(NR) \), with \( R \ll N^2 \). All calculations use this fixed CP format.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-rewiring-the-system&quot;&gt;2. Rewiring the System&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To remove the \( k \)-th orbital, TFHD uses a &lt;strong&gt;nilpotent generator&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; \( \eta_k \), like instructions to rewire a circuit:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[
\eta_k = \sum_{i=1}^{k-1} t_{1,i}^{(k)} f_k^\dagger f_i + \sum_{1 \leq i &amp;lt; j &amp;lt; k} t_{2,ij}^{(k)} f_k^\dagger f_k^\dagger f_j f_i,
\]&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where \( f_i^\dagger, f_i \) add or remove an electron in orbital \( i \), and \( t_{1,i}^{(k)}, t_{2,ij}^{(k)} \) adjust electron movements (single or paired). The \( t_{2,ij}^{(k)} \) are factorized for efficiency. The transformation \( S_k = 1 + \eta_k \) reshapes the Hamiltonian into&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[
\tilde{H}^{(k)} = S_k^{-1} H^{(k)} S_k,
\]&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;all in CP format.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This splits the system by whether the \( k \)-th orbital is unoccupied (\( P_k = 1 - \hat{n}_k \), \( n_k = 0 \)) or occupied (\( Q_k = \hat{n}_k \), \( n_k = 1 \)). The transformed Hamiltonian has four blocks:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[
\tilde{H}^{(k)} = \begin{pmatrix}
P_k \tilde{H}^{(k)} P_k &amp;amp; P_k \tilde{H}^{(k)} Q_k \\
Q_k \tilde{H}^{(k)} P_k &amp;amp; Q_k \tilde{H}^{(k)} Q_k
\end{pmatrix}.
\]&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make \( \tilde{H}^{(k)} \) &lt;strong&gt;block-upper-triangular&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, we impose the &lt;strong&gt;Bloch equation&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[
Q_k \tilde{H}^{(k)} P_k = Q_k S_k^{-1} H^{(k)} S_k P_k = 0.
\]&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This ensures the occupied subspace (\( Q_k \)) does not influence the unoccupied subspace (\( P_k \))—like a one-way network.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-fine-tuning-the-rewiring&quot;&gt;3. Fine-Tuning the Rewiring&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To enforce \( Q_k \tilde{H}^{(k)} P_k = 0 \), TFHD solves &lt;strong&gt;residual equations&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; in CP format:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[
\langle \Phi_{k \to i} | \tilde{H}^{(k)} | \Phi_0 \rangle = 0, \quad \langle \Phi_{kk \to ij} | \tilde{H}^{(k)} | \Phi_0 \rangle = 0,
\]&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;\( \Phi_0 \) is the reference state (e.g., Hartree-Fock),&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;\( \Phi_{k \to i} \) is a single excitation (electron moved to orbital \( k \)),&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;\( \Phi_{kk \to ij} \) is a double excitation (two electrons moved to \( k \)).&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These residual conditions arise from the Bloch equation, ensuring that no matrix elements connect \( P_k \) to \( Q_k \). Solving them adjusts \( t_{1,i}^{(k)}, t_{2,ij}^{(k)} \), like tweaking circuit knobs to eliminate signal leakage. Once solved:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[
\tilde{H}^{(k)} = \begin{bmatrix}
P_k \tilde{H}^{(k)} P_k &amp;amp; P_k \tilde{H}^{(k)} Q_k \\
0 &amp;amp; Q_k \tilde{H}^{(k)} Q_k
\end{bmatrix},
\]&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;achieving a block-upper-triangular structure while retaining the CP format.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-shrinking-the-system&quot;&gt;4. Shrinking the System&lt;&#x2F;h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TFHD removes the \( k \)-th orbital by projecting onto the unoccupied subspace:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\[
H^{(k-1)} = P_k \tilde{H}^{(k)} P_k,
\]&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;yielding a smaller Hamiltonian \( H^{(k-1)} \) with \( k-1 \) orbitals, still in CP format. This preserves all physics (e.g., energy levels). Projecting to \( P_k \) focuses on states where orbital \( k \) is empty—ideal for downfolding virtual orbitals.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process repeats, shrinking the system one orbital at a time and yielding a compressed Hamiltonian with:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Memory&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: ~\( O(N^3) \) instead of ~\( O(N^4 )\)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Computation&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: ~\( O(N^4) \) (with singles and doubles), or ~\( O(N^3) \) (with singles only)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-it-matters-classical-power-quantum-future&quot;&gt;Why It Matters: Classical Power, Quantum Future&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TFHD’s CP structure saves resources on classical computers and is &lt;strong&gt;quantum-ready&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. We use &lt;strong&gt;block-encoding-based circuits&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; for tensor contractions to:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compress data&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Create the initial CP format by factorizing tensors&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adjust coefficients&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Solve residuals for \( t_{1,i}^{(k)}, t_{2,ij}^{(k)} \) via quantum circuits&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Block encoding maps rank-2 CP tensors into quantum circuits, requiring:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fewer Qubits&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: \( O( \log N + \log R )\), reducing thousands to dozens&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fast Circuits&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: Gate depth ~\( O(N^2 \log(1&#x2F;\epsilon)) \) for energy accuracy \( \epsilon \)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On quantum hardware:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quantum Native&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: TFHD maps CP components directly into block-encoded quantum circuits, implementing Quantum Tensor Contractions Natively, by composition.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fewer Shots&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;: No Quantum Phase Estimation or  Quantum Singular Value Transform is required&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each CP term becomes a rank-2 unitary block. Tensor contractions—used to compute energies and update residuals—are simulated directly as quantum circuits.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-bigger-picture-a-new-approach&quot;&gt;The Bigger Picture: A New Approach&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TFHD embodies three key principles:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compact Data Representation&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;:    CP decomposition distills vast, complex tensors into a small set of meaningful components—like summarizing an entire library into a few essential volumes.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resource-Efficient Quantum Mapping&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;:    Block-encoded circuits translate these compact components directly into quantum operations, minimizing qubit and gate overhead.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accurate Simplification&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;:    The method reduces computational complexity without sacrificing physical accuracy, preserving the essential features of the system.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Future directions could improve CP fitting, extend TFHD to dynamic systems, or integrate machine learning for automated orbital selection.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion-redefining-quantum-simulation&quot;&gt;Conclusion: Redefining Quantum Simulation&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TFHD transforms quantum simulation with a one-time CP tensor compression. It rewires the system using a &lt;strong&gt;nilpotent generator&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;, restructures the Hamiltonian into four blocks, applies the &lt;strong&gt;Bloch equation&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; to achieve block triangularization, and tunes it via &lt;strong&gt;residual equations&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;. Finally, it projects to \( P_k \) to shrink the system. Block-encoding circuits ensure quantum efficiency, with quantum gate depth growing only with &lt;strong&gt;CP Tensor size&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;CP rank&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TFHD is the &lt;strong&gt;Quantum JPEG&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;:  accelerating drug discovery for cancer and Alzheimer’s, advancing clean energy through hydrogen and CO2 catalysts, and driving quantum computing innovations. TFHD bridges classical and quantum computing, empowering solutions to humanity’s greatest challenges with the elegance of a compressed image.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
